During my PhD, I knew a researcher that
would storm down the hallways. He'd walk
extremely fast, as fast as he could to
get from one end to the other. You'd
hear him studying closer immediately
after he left his lab all the way down
the hall. I'm a big proponent of
exercise, so it didn't really strike me
as curious. But this wasn't exactly
exercise. And it turns out what might
have seemed peculiar to some is probably
something that we should all be doing,
especially once you hear the data on
what kind of an effect it has on
preventing death of all causes. We're
going to be covering Vilpas. I'll
explain what that is, what impact that
they have on your mortality risk, how
much to do, and how to do them properly.
Let's get into the science. We're
talking about intermittent physical
activity. No, not exercise. In fact, I
like uh Dr. Brad Stanfield's definition.
Exercise snacks is what he calls it.
It's a pretty apt name, but maybe even
too uh exercisy because we're not
talking about doing any explicit
exercise, just a slight shift in our
day-to-day activities. We'll get into uh
some of the examples later. In a massive
analysis, researchers tracked data from
25,000 individuals fitness trackers over
seven years and tried to understand what
impact vigorous intermittent lifestyle
physical activity or vilpas had on all-c
cause mortality as well as two major
contributors to death cardiovascular
disease and cancer. They compared those
that engaged in one or more vilas
compared to those that engaged in none.
Here we have that data on all cause
mortality. The vertical axis is the
hazard ratio or the amount of reduced
risk compared to not engaging in vilpa.
The horizontal is the amount of vilpa
bouts or moments a person engages in
with more going rightward. The histogram
there is simply indicates the number of
participants in each category. Now, as
you can see, the line for all-c cause
mortality immediately drops, indicating
a reduced risk of mortality from simply
engaging in one one minute vila, and the
relationship indicates further benefit
of doing more bouts. But a large chunk
of the relationship occurs from just
doing one. Look at that. A video title
that actually delivers. But we're not
done because we have to get into some of
the specifics. For one, if we pop open
the cardiovascular disease mortality
data and the cancer data, we can see
it's roughly the same. So, we know that
at least part of the all-c cause
mortality reduction is likely through a
reduced cardiovascular mortality and
cancer mortality. But, as an astute
observer will note, these are
associations. But fortunately, the
researchers did do a series of
statistical adjustments to control for
different factors. Here they are. a lot
of obvious possible confounding factors,
variables that could explain this
reduction in risk and need to be
accounted for to establish a more secure
relationship between Vilpa and reduced
mortality. But I will note that they
don't control for everything. For
example, note that they don't control
for things like blood cholesterol, blood
pressure, blood sugar, and so on. Why
not? This is actually a great thing.
They're avoiding something called a
mediator bias. These factors, blood
pressure, blood sugar and so on are
mediators, meaning that they contribute
to disease like high blood sugar and
diabetes. However, Vilpa's mechanism of
action may work through these mediators.
So, if you remove them from the
analysis, you're flattening the effect
and have a good chance of missing a
relationship that would otherwise be
there. It's a lot like uh I don't know
lifting weights and removing muscle gain
as a factor when measuring strength
since muscle directly contributes to
strength even if not exclusively it
might eliminate the relationship between
lifting weights and strength. So like I
said it's a good thing that they didn't
over adjust here. They also had some
timing mismatch uh between the blood
sugar cholesterol and blood pressure
data and the data that they used to
determine vulpa. Another good reason not
to add these adjustments. Speaking to
that, what are examples of Velpa that
you can implement in your own life? And
can we get more objective measures if we
are engaging in Vilpa? We'll address
those two questions next or next after
this quick point. There's more on the
optimal amounts of Vilpa, maximum
amounts where doing more won't do much
more for you. And the answers to
questions like, does this apply if I
exercise regularly or um I'm a generally
healthy person. Do things change for me?
Anyway, I'm covering uh more in an
in-depth analysis of all that in my
extended version of this video. If
you're interested in having all the
details and specialized takeaways, check
out the Aphysionic Insiders, my premium
research review, which also includes a
private podcast, live sessions with me,
an active community, written research
reviews with short summaries, and more.
The link to join is in theuh
description. If you want an honest
appraisal of research and how to apply
it to your life, it's the place to be.
I'd really love to have you there. So,
what are examples of Vilpa? Let's start
general and then let's define it more
specifically. Like I said, this isn't
structured exercise. This is everyday
activity. For example, very fast
walking. Remember my professor? The guy
was on a mission everywhere that he
went. I really uh think that he'd walk
right through someone if they got in his
way. Other options include climbing
stairs quickly, uh carrying heavy
shopping bags quickly, uh walking uphill
quickly, uh and really just anything
that could be leisurely and you choose
to supercharge it with speed and
purpose. Okay, that's still pretty
general. The researchers did use some
more exact methods. They're not perfect,
but they're a good benchmark to assess
if you're going in the right direction.
So, these numbers come from unpublished
validation study uh also used by the
researchers to create these cut offs for
vigorous intensity. Some of the metrics
are based on V2 max. Not helpful to
most, but I'll mention it anyway. The
physical activity should be above 64% of
your V2 max. As for more day-to-day
measures, it's a combination of two
metrics. One, you should be achieving
equal to or above 77% of your maximum
heart rate as well as a perceived
intensity of 15 or higher based on the
Borg scale. No, not related to Star
Trek. You can pause to see what that
should look like right here. Achieving
both the more objective heart rate
metric and the more subjective Borg
scale for about one minute gives you
credit for one Vilpa bout which you can
then cash in for one Zorbuk which is
then donated to achieve a Zaltterron
status. These names get ridiculous. I
can't help myself. So overall the point
here is that you don't need to exercise
to achieve significant reductions in
mortality risk if you simply keep doing
the same things that you always do but
ramp up the intensity of daily tasks
like walking or climbing stairs based on
the metrics that we outlined. of 77% or
greater of heart rate maximum and a 15
or greater on the Borg scale for about 1
minute. You will achieve a vigorous
intermittent lifestyle physical activity
bout or vila bout. And the evidence
suggests doing at least one to two of
these per day is related to reduce risk
which is pretty amazing isn't it? Bao
Vilpaorg Zerblut Linkrad Tang Zilor Bin
Finra. No, I'm not having a stroke. You
just haven't played the Sims before, so
you don't get it. But what I'm saying is
there's another video for you right
here. So Vulpa your way to it. Click
with intensity.